דף Daf is קעג Kuf Ayin Gimmel 173. Let's take it from
the very top, okay? And the גמרא Gemara had a discussion the
other day about a pretty much like a what I was calling
a bare bond, IOU, I, Dov Lindzer, owe you a thousand dollars.
So who's the you, because it's assumed to be any, whichever person
is holding on to it. But that led the גמרא Gemara to
discussion and now we're going to just focus on this point, that
the משנה Mishnah says if you have two people with the same
name, somebody cannot take a שטר shtar against them. But it sounds
like they, if I have a document that says, you know, Eli
owes Dov Lindzer a thousand dollars and I'm bearing it and I'm
holding on to it, it's valid, he can't claim it came from
the other Dov Lindzer. Okay, so that's the implication of
the משנה, Mishnah, that
the person themselves that has somebody else with their name can have
a document written in their name if they're the ones bearing it.
Then we don't worry that it fell from the other person with
the exact same name. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara says though
fine, we get that, that makes sense as the גמרא Gemara said
yesterday, we're not חיישינן לנפילה דחד, chashinan lenifila dechad, that exactly that
one person that has my name dropped it and I found it.
No, I'm bearing it with my name, presumably I am the one
that it refers to. But now it says the top of קעג
עמוד א, Kuf Ayin Gimmel Amud Aleph, והא דתניא, ve-ha de-tanya, fine,
that's the explanation of the משנה, Mishnah, but that which we taught
in a ברייתא, braita, כשם שאין מוציאין שטר חוב זה על זה,
keshaym she'ain motzi'in shtar chov zeh al zeh, the same way I
can't take a this, you know, this debt document against the other
person with my name, it says I Dov Lindzer owe Dov Lindzer
a thousand dollars or whatever it is, so who is the creditor,
am I the debtor? So the same way I can't do that,
כך אין מוציאין על אחרים, kach ein motzi'in al acherim, but I
can't even take a document against other people that says Eli owes
Dov Lindzer a thousand dollars. Why not? I mean I'm Dov Lindzer,
I'm holding onto it, yeah there's another Dov Lindzer around, but obviously
I'm the one it refers to. So why can't I do that?
So במאי קמיפלגי, be-mai kamifligi, what's that debate about whether I can
do that or not? So באותיות נקנות במסירה קמיפלגי. be-otiyot niknot bimesira
kamifligi. The question is does handing over a document make transfer the
debt in the document? תנא דידן סבר אותיות נקנות במסירה. tana didan
savar otiyot niknot bimesira. Handing it over does transfer. So the point
is now we're sort of shifting gears a little and saying that
you know the fact that I have a document that says that
Eli owes Dov Lindzer, maybe it is referring to the other Dov
Lindzer. Maybe I do have to worry about that. What would I
do to counter that concern? So the claim that no no no,
אותיות נקנות במסירה otiyot niknot bimesira counters that concern. That means that
even somehow if it originally was for the other Dov Lindzer, the
fact that you're holding it is a presumption that he transferred it
to you. Either you're holding it as a presumption that it was
written in your name or a presumption that he transferred it to
you. Now maybe that's not enough to hand me the שטר shtar
to transfer it to me. Maybe you need to do something else,
you need another supporting document, you need other types of things. No,
if you hold the position אותיות נקנות במסירה, otiyot niknot bimesira, all
you need to do to transfer the debt is to hand it
over. You can even hand it over to somebody whose name isn't
in it at all. That would be the standard case. I have
a document that says Eli owes Dov Lindzer a thousand dollars and
I hand it over to Charlie, Charlie's not here, okay, now he
owes Charlie even though it has my name in it. Okay, because
once you say אותיות נקנות במסירה, otiyot niknot bimesira, what are you
saying? You're saying that if somebody is holding a document it doesn't
matter who the name of the creditor is. There's a presumption that
the debt was transferred to that person. So you get that? If
we're living in a world where אותיות נקנות במסירה, otiyot niknot bimesira,
that means Charlie comes to court with a document that says Eli
owes Dov Lindzer a thousand dollars and the court says fine fine
Eli go pay Charlie. What do you mean go pay Charlie? It
says Dov Lindzer. No, אותיות נקנות במסירה, otiyot niknot bimesira, the fact
that he's holding the שטר shtar is a presumption that the debt
was transferred to him. Okay, so therefore the גמרא Gemara says here's
what we could say. We could say you are חיישינן לנפילה, chashinan
lenifila, not like we said before, okay, but if אותיות נקנות במסירה,
otiyot niknot bimesira, that basically says that you know it doesn't matter
if that's a possibility, if that's a theoretical possibility. אותיות נקנות במסירה
otiyot niknot bimesira means anybody who's holding the שטר, shtar, even if
it's the wrong name, is presumed to be the creditor of the
שטר. shtar. One minute, so תנא דידן סבר אותיות נקנות במסירה, tana
didan savar otiyot niknot bimesira, ותנא ברייתא סבר אין אותיות נקנות במסירה.
ve-tana braita savar ein otiyot niknot bimesira. No, that does not true,
if it's got the wrong name it doesn't. Doesn't work. And once
if it's got, I mean, forget that, let me put it this
way, you can't transfer it just by handing it over. You can't
transfer it just by handing it over. And if somebody says this
שטר shtar is mine and the debt is now to me, and
it's got the wrong name, we would say, no, it's not. And
if he really did transfer it, bring the other sort of evidence
that he transferred it, but this is not this that does not
transfer. No, well, actually, אותיות נקנות במסירה otiyos niknos be-mesirah means even
the very act of transfer, I'm getting a little ahead of myself
because the next גמרא Gemara is going to be about proving, but
that means even the very act of transfer would require a new
שטר. shtar. Okay, so the very act to effect the transfer would
require a new שטר, shtar, so holding a שטר shtar in a
wrong name is meaningless even for getting proving it. The actual act
of transaction required a new שטר. shtar. So show us the new
שטר. shtar. Okay, so according to this approach, we would theoretically be
concerned that it fell from one Dov Linzer and the other Dov
Linzer founded. Okay. But if אותיות נקנות במסירה, otiyos niknos be-mesirah, that
doesn't matter, because that says whoever's holding the שטר, shtar, it's presumed
that either it was written in his name, or if it's the
wrong name, that it was transferred to him. And if אין אותיות
נקנות במסירה, ein otiyos niknos be-mesirah, it means we do not make
that presumption. And therefore, even in a case of a Dov Linzer
and written in the right name, if there's another person with that
name, we are concerned. So according to this, it's חיישינן לנפילה chashinan
lenefilah in a theoretical sense. But legally does that matter? If אותיות
נקנות במסירה, otiyos niknos be-mesirah, that legally doesn't matter. Any שטר shtar
you're holding is presumed to be yours. And if אין אותיות נקנות
במסירה, ein otiyos niknos be-mesirah, then it does matter. Dov, you had
a question before? It's been answered. Okay, yes. So in according to
the position that אותיות נקנות במסירה, otiyos niknos be-mesirah, so is it
just as ironclad? To the extent is it just as good as
any regular completely so you know... Well, no, because the original original
person the money is owed to could always be מוחל mochel it.
No, I mean in terms of just in terms of like, you
know, how challengeable it is, is it any more or less challengeable
than a regular שטר? shtar? I mean because...
Yeah, you could demand קיום שטרות kiyom shtaros and all that stuff.
Would you do that in a regular... Yeah, yeah, there's nothing different.
The only thing is that the original creditor can be מוחל. mochel.
Now the גמרא Gemara says ואיבעית אימא, ve-iba'is eima, if you want
I could say,
because actually what I was doing, if you were paying attention a
minute ago,
was folding in two things: the act of transaction, the debt, the
loan is transferred by the handing over, and that once we're going
to say that, we're
going to presume any שטר shtar you're holding that you
actually, you know, you're
the one that's owed money to, it's been transferred to you. But
those are really separable things, right? One is what do you require
to effect the transaction, and the other is what do you need
to do to prove that it actually took place. So now the
גמרא's Gemara going to move to that step. ואיבעית אימא, ve-iba'is eima,
if you want I'll tell you דכולי עלמא אותיות נקנות במסירה. de-chulei
alma otiyos niknos be-mesirah. In terms of whether did you actually achieve
transferring the debt when you handed it over to the other person,
the answer is yes. So if I have a שטר shtar written
that Eli owes me a thousand dollars, Dov Linzer, and I give
it to Charlie, he now owes Charlie the thousand dollars. But that
doesn't mean that Charlie's going to be believed to make that claim
in court. It's a שטר shtar written in the wrong name. Okay,
so the question is דהכא בצריך להביא ראיה קמיפלגי. de-hacha be-tzarich lehavi
rayah kamifligi. The question is do you have to bring do we
does the holding of the שטר shtar even with a wrong name,
it's presumed that a debt was transferred to you? Or do we
say no, that act might have transferred it, but prove to me
that that's what happened. Maybe you found it on the floor. Maybe
Dov dropped it. Okay. דהכא בצריך להביא ראיה קמיפלגי, de-hacha be-tzarich lehavi
rayah kamifligi, the debate is whether you have to bring a proof
that that's what happened. תנא דידן סבר, Tanna didan savar, אין צריך
להביא ראיה, ein tzarich lehavi rayah, you don't have to bring a
proof. So even if even if somebody was holding on to a
שטר shtar with the wrong name, it would be a presumption that
the debt was transferred to him. So certainly if there are two
Dov Linzers and one Dov Linzer is handing holding onto the שטר,
shtar, it's a presumption that either it was written in his name,
which is ninety-nine percent likely, or even if it was written in
the other person's name, that it was handed to him. So either
way he can collect from this. Okay, so you don't have to
prove that that's what happened. ותנא ברא סבר, ve-Tanna bara savar, but
the other, the exterior תנא, Tanna, holds צריך להביא ראיה tzarich lehavi
rayah that you have to bring a proof. So the same way
if Charlie's holding on to a document that says that Eli owes
Dov Linzer, we would say, you know what, maybe he handed it
to you and that's transferred the debt, okay, but maybe you found
it on the floor. Holding your שטר shtar doesn't prove that that's
what happened. Go ahead and prove it. So that would be if
it was written in the wrong name. Obviously it's according to this
you would have to prove, which is a very reasonable position. But
now what we're doing is we're extending that to the case of
two Dov Linzers, which is a harder case, right? Because then I
have a שטר shtar again that says that Eli owes Dov Linzer
a thousand dollars. So what we have to first say is wait,
חיישינן לנפילה chashinan lenefilah even דחד, de-chad, maybe it fell from the
other Dov Linzer. And once we're worried about that, then we have
to say so the fact that you're holding onto it isn't proof
that you're the creditor, right, and you would צריך להביא ראיה. tzarich
lehavi rayah. So again, that becomes a little strange. We get the
צריך להביא ראיה tzarich lehavi rayah when it's written in the wrong
person's name, but when it's written in the in the in the
name matching... is the name in the שטר, shtar, it seems a
little bit bizarre to be saying צריך להביא ראיה. tsarich lehavi ra'aya.
That's essentially saying חיישינן לנפילה דחד. chayshinan lenifila dechad. We're concerned that
one person dropped it and therefore you have to, right? So basically
the way the גמרא Gemara sort of is structuring it is: okay,
if you have if here's your guy, here's your I don't know
why he's very tall, okay, ראובן בן שמעון, Reuven ben Shimon, okay,
and it says sorry, owes ראובן בן שמעון, Reuven ben Shimon, okay?
So obviously he should be presumed. But here's the other ראובן בן
שמעון. Reuven ben Shimon. Okay, make him look a little different. ראובן
בן שמעון. Reuven ben Shimon. So do we presume that you're the
owner? Okay? So if we say so here's the possibility, okay, we'll
make a little anyway, חיישינן לנפילה דחד, chayshinan lenifila dechad, right? Are
we afraid, do we say, are we afraid of the tiny tiny
possibility that this guy dropped it and the same guy found it?
Okay, so if the answer is no, so then it works. He
can bring it because there's no, we don't even begin to suspect
that. If the answer is yes, right? Maybe this is what happened,
he fell it fell and he found it, okay, so then the
question is, if אותיות נקנות במסירה otiot niknot bemesira and now we
really understand plus אין צריך להביא ראיה, ein tsarich lehavi ra'aya, which
basically means whoever is holding onto equals whoever is holding the שטר
shtar is the presumed creditor. So that would be even the wrong
name, right? Even a wrong name. So that's a pretty that's a
pretty weird position, right? That's a weird I mean that you could
have a wrong name but you're holding on as you're the presumed
creditor, then it works, okay? Then it works. If we say that
אותיות נקנות במסירה otiot niknot bemesira and אין צריך להביא ראיה. ein
tsarich lehavi ra'aya. But if we don't say that, if we say
that if you're holding onto a wrong שטר shtar name, you have
to bring a proof, then it doesn't work. But the irony being
that here even though it's the right name, we get to say
that it doesn't work if I don't know if that
helped people. Anyway, we get to
say that it doesn't work if I get the idea that it
doesn't work if it's the wrong name in the שטר, shtar, but
it's the right name in the שטר. shtar. But once you start
by saying חיישינן לנפילה דחד, chayshinan lenifila dechad, we're concerned that even
though it's written in my name, says another person with that name,
so maybe it came from that person, then we're going to say,
okay, then if we then, once we have that concern, then we're
going to say that wrong name or the right name, once we
have that concern that even one that it fell from that guy
and you found it, and we're going to say צריך להביא ראיה,
tsarich lehavi ra'aya, then we're not going to be able to presume
that it's yours. He needs another שטר. shtar. What? Yes. Given the
proportionality of the diagram, the little guy could never pick up that
שטר. shtar. Okay, fine. שטר הגדול. shtar hagadol. Anyway, fine. I don't
know if that little decision chart helped. But okay, moving on. Okay,
so now the גמרא Gemara says like this. Okay. אמר אביי מנא
אמינא לה. Amar Abaye mana amina lah. Where'd I know this from?
דתניא, Detanya, we taught in a ברייתא. braita. אחד מן האחים שהשטר
חוב יוצא מתחת ידו Echad min ha'achim shehashtar chov yotzei mitachat yado
oh sorry, I skipped a line. דאתמר, De'itmar, it was taught. אותיות
נקנות במסירה. Otiot niknot bemesira. You can transfer a debt just by
handing it over. אביי אמר צריך להביא ראיה. Abaye amar tsarich lehavi
ra'aya. You have that might work to effect the transfer, but when
you come to בית דין Beis Din with the שטר, shtar, you
need to bring a proof, either with another שטר shtar or with
עדים edim or
whatever, that it actually was transferred to you. רבא אמר אינו צריך
להביא ראיה. Rava amar eino tsarich lehavi ra'aya. You don't have to
bring proof.
אמר אביי, Amar Abaye, says אביי, Abaye, מנא אמינא לה.
mana amina lah. Where do I get this
idea from that you have to bring a proof? דתניא, Detanya, we
taught in a ברייתא. braita. אחד מן האחים שהשטר חוב יוצא מתחת
ידו. Echad min ha'achim shehashtar chov yotzei mitachat yado. So one of
the brothers, father died, יעקב Yaakov died, and now ראובן Reuven comes
to בית דין Beis Din with a שטר shtar that says that
מרדכי Mordechai owes יעקב Yaakov a thousand dollars. Or he goes to
מרדכי, Mordechai, and he says, 'This is it's all mine.' Obviously the
brothers inherit from the father, so you should logically assume that the
debt is owed to all the brothers equally, but ראובן Reuven says,
'No, no, no, we split up the estate and this debt is
all mine right now, and so you pay just me.' So you
got it? It's written in the wrong name, in the name of
the father, okay? It's a little different this case because it's not
like a completely unrelated name. But nevertheless, there's no presumption that it's
all ראובן's Reuven debt, the presumption is that it's all the brothers'
debt equally. Okay? So so it says, עליו להביא ראיה. alav lehavi
ra'aya. So he has to bring a proof that it's all his
debt and we don't presume that his holding it means that it's
been transferred to him. So מאי לאו, mai lav, would it not
be true for others? If you're holding on to a שטר shtar
from somebody who from in a complete different person's name, you I
mean you would think it's a קל וחומר, kal v'chomer, you would
have to bring a proof that it's been transferred to you. ורמי
בר חמא Verami bar Chama and Rava says nope, שאני אחין דשמטו
מהדדי, shani achin d'shamtu mehadadi, brothers are different because brothers snatch things
from one another. So when you're growing up, hey, he stole my
toy. Okay, anyway, so you're all living in the same house, you
have access to it, so there we're concerned that because you had
access to it and so on you actually took it illegitimately and
you have to prove that it legitimately was transferred to you. But
if I have a שטר shtar that says that Eli owes Charlie
a thousand dollars, how did I get access to that שטר, shtar,
right? Charlie doesn't let me into his you know safety deposit box
or whatever. So the fact that I have the שטר, shtar, אין
צריך להביא ראיה. ein tzarich lehavi ra'aya. But in the case of
brothers, צריך להביא ראיה. tzarich lehavi ra'aya. You stole it, that's what
Charlie's saying. I understand, but we're not concerned about that. We're much
more concerned in the brother case than in the case of somebody
who's not a brother. איכא דאמרי, ika d'amri, others say אמר רבא
מנא אמינא לה, amar Rava m'na amina lah, that it started the
other way. Rava says where do I know this idea that you
don't have to bring a proof? דתניא אחד מן האחין שהשטר חוב
יוצא מתחת ידו, d'tanya echad min ha'achin shehashtar chov yotzei mitachat yado,
עליו להביא ראיה. alav lehavi ra'aya. So this brother had to bring
a proof. So Rava starts by saying this is a proof to
me because we're specifically talking about a case of brothers. אחין הוא
דשמטו מהדדי, achin hu d'shamtu mehadadi, by brothers where they can you
know snatch things from one another you have to bring a proof.
אבל אחריני, aval achrinei, other people לא, lo, would not be a
proof and even if it's in a different person's name
there's a presumption that it's yours.
ואביי v'Abaye and Abaye would say back אחין אצטריכא ליה. achin itztricha
lei. No, no, no, it needed to tell us even in the
case of brothers you need a proof because you could use the
idea that they snatch things to go the opposite way. סלקא דעתך
אמינא, salka daitach amina, I would have thought to say כיון דשמטו
מהדדי, keivan d'shamtu mehadadi, since it's natural for brothers to be snatching
from one another אימא מזדהר זהירי ולא צריכי להביא ראיה, eima mizdahar
zehiri v'lo tzarichi lehavi ra'aya, maybe they are even more careful from
one another than they are from strangers. So maybe it's even a
you know, so there I should דוקא davka presume that it was
legitimately transferred because of course they would have been on their guard
from one another. קא משמע לן, ka mashma lan, we don't say
that. But it's all part according to Abaye of the normal rule
of צריך להביא ראיה tzarich lehavi ra'aya and Rava says the normal
rule is אין צריך להביא ראיה ein tzarich lehavi ra'aya and brothers
are the exception. Okay, so that's the debate. דלהא דתניא, d'leha d'tanya,
so now we've got it. So we've got the debate of whether
in general we say that when אותיות נקנות במסירה otiot niknot b'mesira
and you have a שטר shtar in a wrong name, do you
have to bring a ראיה? ra'aya? We have a debate of with
this two Reuven ben Shimons, you know two Dov Linzers and I
have a שטר shtar that says Dov Linzer, you know you owe
Dov Linzer a thousand dollars, does that work or not? The debate
there is the one that says you do not have to bring,
excuse me, that it does work. I can use my שטר shtar
against Eli and he can't claim it's the other Dov Linzer. Is
either because לא חיישינן לנפילה דחד, lo chayshinan l'nefila d'chad, which makes
a ton of sense, or even if we're חיישינן, chayshinan, if we're
living in a world where אותיות נקנות במסירה otiot niknot b'mesira and
אין צריך להביא ראיה, ein tzarich lehavi ra'aya, anybody who's bearing a
שטר shtar is believed to be that you know the person to
whom the money is owed. Okay, and the ברייתא braita that says
that I can't bring the שטר shtar against Eli, he can always
claim it's the other Dov Linzer means חיישינן לנפילה דחד chayshinan l'nefila
d'chad and צריך להביא ראיה. tzarich lehavi ra'aya. Okay, A, we're afraid
he dropped it and B, the fact that you are holding onto
it doesn't presume that you are the right owner because you always
need supporting proof. Yes. You'd use that same סברה sevara that had
been rejected about the brothers for the two Dov Linzers in the
same town? Yeah, I think that that's absolutely correct. So now the
גמרא Gemara says okay, so now we've explained that debate about whether
we can take, I can use my שטר shtar here against Eli.
Okay, now, but the גמרא Gemara says אלא להא דתניא, ela leha
d'tanya, but now we've got a third debate, that which we taught
in the ברייתא, braita, כשם שמוציאין הן שטר
חוב עליהן כך מוציאין זה על זה.
keshem shemotzi'in hen
shtar
chov aleihen kach motzi'in zeh al zeh. ובמאי קמיפלגי? u'v'mai kamipalgi? This
sounds crazy. The ברייתא braita is even more, this ברייתא braita
is even more lenient, I'll call it, than the משנה. Mishna.
Not only can I use
a שטר חוב shtar chov that says Eli owes Dov Linzer a
thousand dollars to get the money from Eli, but if I have
a שטר shtar that says Dov Linzer owes Dov Linzer a thousand
dollars, I can use it against my cousin. Okay, he's also Dov
Linzer. Now that's crazy. He could say it's the opposite. He was
the creditor and I was the debtor and I paid off my
debt and he gave me the שטר shtar back. Of course that
would be crazy, don't give the שטר shtar back, tear it up
or whatever. But we're going to see another even more likely scenario.
I might as well tell you, you know what the more likely
scenario is? What's the הלכה? halacha? The הלכה halacha is the לוה
loveh can go to בית דין beis din to עדים edim and
get them to write a שטר shtar before the money is borrowed.
I can go to בית דין beis din and say go write
a שטר shtar that Dov Linzer borrowed from Eli a thousand dollars
and give it to me, because I'm the party that's hurt by
it, right? And then once Eli lends me the money I'll give
him the שטר. shtar. So let's say I go to בית דין
beis din and say I'm planning on borrowing a thousand dollars from
my cousin, write a שטר shtar that Dov Linzer borrowed from Dov
Linzer a thousand dollars. And then, okay, because I'm the party being
hurt they can write this. And then I turn around and I
say no, he's the one who owes me the money, I'm not
the one who owes him the money. Okay, so anyway it's a
little crazy how you could say since you could easily imagine the
positions are flipped, how that could work. So the גמרא Gemara wants
to understand what is the logic behind that. So במאי קמיפלגי, bemai
kamiflegi, what’s that debate about? Because שטר ללווה ואף על פי שאין
מלווה עמו קמיפלגי. shtar l’loveh v’af al pi she’ein malveh imo kamiflegi.
The question is exactly this, will we write a שטר shtar for
the לווה loveh without the מלווה malveh being present, which we normally
know is the principle? תנא דידן tana didan סבר savar that the
תנא tana of our משנה mishna holds כותבין שטר ללווה ואף על
פי שאין מלווה עמו, kotvin shtar l'loveh v'af al pi she'ein malveh
imo, that you write it to the לווה loveh without the מלווה
malveh being present, and therefore זימנין דאזיל לגבי ספרא zimnin d'azil l'gabei
safra וסהדי, v'sahadei, you go in front of the scribe and the
witnesses, ואמר להו v'amar lehu כתובי לי שטרא, kitvu li shtra, go
write me a שטר shtar דבעינא למיזף מיוסף בן שמעון חברי, d'beina
l'meizaf miYosef ben Shimon chavrei, I want to go borrow from יוסף
בן שמעון Yosef ben Shimon my friend who happens to have the
same name as me. So go ahead and write a שטר shtar
that יוסף בן שמעון Yosef ben Shimon borrowed from יוסף בן שמעון
Yosef ben Shimon and then when he lends me the money I’ll
give it to him. Okay, and they somehow did not realize that
this could easily be abused and therefore they’ll write it to him
and then he’ll flip it around. So because of that possibility we
do not allow one of them to take the money against the
other one. Okay. It’s- right. It’s yes, yes, they have the same
name.
That’s a case.
Now of course it’s interesting that we’re not concerned about the fact
that you know I went ahead and I paid it up and
he gave it to me and then I just went around and
turned around and used it. But that’s because I’m stupid. If he
gives me, you know, he should say I’m not giving you the
שטר, shtar, we’re going to tear it up, you know, or I’ll
write a שובר shovar or something, whatever, I don’t know, but anyway.
But that presumably is something that you know that they could protect
against.
בדיוק. bidyuk. Exactly. Okay, but why do they no longer discuss the
idea of having some sort of identity? No, we’re going to get
to that, but this is why you don’t allow it without the
same identity. If they have the exact same names and it’s not
given of more identification, will it be valid? There’s ways to make
it work without that. תנא ברא tana bara סבר, savar, the other
תנא tana holds אין כותבין שטר ללווה עד שיהא מלווה עמו, ein
kotvin shtar l'loveh ad she'yehei malveh imo, that no, we demand that
the מלווה malveh be with me. So if I come with my
cousin to בית דין beis din and say write a שטר shtar
that I’m going to borrow from my cousin a thousand dollars and
they're זבולון וזבולון, Zevulun v'Zevulun, a thousand dollars, then you know my
cousin is going to make sure that he gets that שטר shtar
and gives me the thousand dollars before we all leave the room
and that I don’t walk out of that room with that שטר,
shtar, you know, alone and then I’m going to turn the tables
on him.
All right, still that seems like
that is just way too dangerous and open for abuse. So that
seems like a pretty strange position that we can use it when
they have the exact same names, the borrower and the lender. All
right. It's only if they're in the same city, right? Yeah, yeah,
yeah, but that we would allow it, that seems crazy. נמצא אחד
בין שטרותיו ששטרא של יוסף בן שמעון פרוע שטרא שניהם פרועין. nimtza
echad bein shtarosav she'shtra shel Yosef ben Shimon parua shtra sheneihem pruin.
If I find among my documents a receipt that says I paid
up, יוסף בן שמעון Yosef ben Shimon paid up his, you know,
his IOU, then I don’t know which יוסף בן שמעון Yosef ben
Shimon it refers to. So if I’m an honest guy, I mean
if I’m not an honest guy I’ll just throw it out, I
don’t have to report, I won’t report to the court that I
found this receipt here. But if I’m an honest guy and then
I don’t know which יוסף בן שמעון Yosef ben Shimon it refers
to, I can't collect from either of them. So גמרא Gemara says
like this, טעמא דנמצא, taama d’nimtza, the reason is because I found
this receipt. הא לא נמצא מצי מפיק, ha lo nimtza matzi mafik,
but if I didn’t find the receipt I could collect from יוסף
בן שמעון. Yosef ben Shimon. So what’s the scenario? The scenario is
I have two שטרות. shtaros. One says יוסף בן שמעון Yosef ben
Shimon owes me a thousand and the other says יוסף בן שמעון
Yosef ben Shimon owes me, owes me ten thousand. One refers to
one יוסף בן שמעון, Yosef ben Shimon, one to the other. I
have a receipt, I can’t use either. But the גמרא Gemara says,
but even if you didn’t have the receipt you couldn’t use either,
right? Because that’s what we said before.
Either one you go to will tell you it’s the other one.
So the גמרא Gemara says הא לא נמצא מצי מפיק, ha lo
nimtza matzi mafik, if you didn’t have the receipt you could use
your שטר shtar against them? והתנן דלא אחד יכול להוציא עליהם שטר
חוב תנן,
v'hatnan d'lo echad yakhol l'hotzi
aleihem shtar chov tnan, but we said that somebody cannot, you know,
use a document against them because they’ll always claim it’s the other
one. So who needs the receipt? These documents can’t be used regardless.
So the גמרא Gemara says
very- by a receipt
you mean an IOU, right? No, it's a receipt. I have in
my possession one document says ראובן בן שמעון Reuven ben Shimon owes
a thousand dollars and one says, wait a minute, ראובן בן שמעון
Reuven ben Shimon owes whatever five thousand dollars. Okay, right? Now I
know that this one refers to this ראובן בן שמעון Reuven ben
Shimon and this one refers to this ראובן בן שמעון, Reuven ben
Shimon, but and but I have here written amongst my documents ראובן
בן שמעון Reuven ben Shimon paid up his שטרא, shtra, paid up
his שטרא. shtra. So ההלכה ha’halacha is since I don’t know which
one this refers to, I can’t use either. Okay, so that’s the-
that's the receipt. But somehow he should be holding on to the
receipt, he trusted me and I’m holding on to the receipt. Okay.
Now the גמרא Gemara actually says, now and but I’m an honest
guy, okay? So you know I said I don’t have my receipt
on you, I’ll get it to you, whatever, but clearly I’m an
honest guy. There’s actually another גמרא Gemara I should mention that actually
says that normally if the מלווה malveh is holding on to the
receipt he doesn't have to be afraid about- worry about it. He
could just assume he pre-wrote it and hasn’t given it yet, right,
if he doesn’t remember the specifics. But this case actually the another
גמרא Gemara says that you found this receipt, here's my dot—I had
a drawer, right, that said here's my file cabinet and it said
paid up שטרות, shtarot, okay? And it had all these שטרות shtarot
which were cut which were torn, which shows that they were paid
up, and in this this was here this receipt that said ראובן
בן שמעון Reuven ben Shimon paid up. So because I found it
amongst those שטרות, shtarot, I know that it's not a receipt I
had intended to give, it really had been paid, and I and
you know, he really had paid it up, that's why I have
to treat this seriously, cause I found it in this drawer, okay,
but I don't know and he trusted me and I am an
honest guy because I'm coming to בית דין beis din now, but
I just forgot which one of them paid up and which one
it goes on. So it says I can't use either. So the
גמרא Gemara says who cares because you've got the receipt? You can't
use either because each one will claim that the שטר shtar is
the other guy, right? I might know which is which, but the
משנה Mishnah says that if I have two ראובן בן שמעון Reuven
ben Shimon שטרות, shtars, like whatever, each שטר shtar I can't use
on either of them. So even without these these שטרות shtaros are
neutralized. So who needs the receipt? So the גמרא Gemara says, so
אמר רב ירמיה, Amar Reb Yirmiyah, so רב ירמיה Reb Yirmiyah has
a great answer. He says במשולשים, bimshulashim, that the שטרות shtaros are—can
be used, cause this says ראובן בן שמעון בן יעקב, Reuven ben
Shimon ben Yaakov, and this says ראובן בן שמעון בן
משה.
Reuven ben Shimon
ben Moshe.
So okay and
this is the משה Moshe one and this is the יעקב Yaakov
one. Okay, so the שטרות shtaros are good. Okay, and but the
receipt makes it that I can't use it. So במשולשים bimshulashim means
what? Three names? Three yeah, three generations. Three generations. Right. So the
גמרא Gemara says, so the גמרא Gemara says ונחזי תברא בשמא דמאן
כתיב, venichzi tavra bishma deman kasiv, so just look, what does the
receipt say? ראובן בן שמעון בן יעקב Reuven ben Shimon ben Yaakov
or ראובן בן שמעון בן משה? Reuven ben Shimon ben Moshe? So
the גמרא Gemara says בשמא דמאן כתיב, bishma deman kasiv, אמר רב
אושעיא במשולשים בשטר ואין משולשים בשובר. Amar Reb Oshayah bimshulashim beshtar veein
mishulashim beshovar. I was really stupid. The שטרות shtaros went three generations,
but the receipt only went two generations. So the שטרות shtaros would
have been fine. I could use this one against ראובן שמעון יעקב
Reuven Shimon Yaakov and this one against ראובן שמעון משה, Reuven Shimon
Moshe, but the receipt said ראובן בן שמעון Reuven ben Shimon paid
up his שטר shtar and I didn't know which one it was
referring to so I can't use either שטר. shtar. That's a good
אוקימתא, ukimta, it's not even so crazy. Okay, so that's one answer.
אביי אמר הכי קאמר. Abaye amar hachi kaamar. No, no, you misunderstood
the משנה, Mishnah, says אביי. Abaye. Here's what the משנה Mishnah says.
נמצא ללווה בין שטרותיו שטר
שיוצא בן שמעון עלי פרוע הדברים עלי שטר שניהם פרועים.
Nimtza leloveh bein
shtarosav shtar
sheyotzei ben Shimon alai parua hadvarim alai shtar sheneihem peruim. So here's
what happened, that this guy is not בן יעקב ben Yaakov or
בן משה, ben Moshe, doesn't say that, but it's not that here,
the מלווה, malveh, here
this guy was the מלווה.
malveh. Okay. It's not that the מלווה malveh had the
receipt. What happened was that this
guy had the receipt. ראובן בן שמעון Reuven ben Shimon paid up.
Okay. And now, so I can still go ahead and collect my
שטר shtar well, actually no, here, wait a minute, let me see
if I get this right. So the לווה loveh has what? The
לווה loveh has the receipt, as he should. Right. And wait a
minute, hold on, let
me just just test thing.
Wait a minute. שטר שיוצא בן שמעון. Shtar sheyotzei ben Shimon. Oh
no no no, I got I'm sorry, I'm sorry.
It completely reverses it. Okay? It's not that
the borrower is a יוסף בן שמעון. Yosef ben Shimon. The lender
is a יוסף בן שמעון, Yosef ben Shimon,
okay? Wait, hold on one second, let me just double check. Yes.
Okay, here the case. Okay, it's the two Dov Linzer cases before,
okay? So here, these are both יוסף בן שמעון, Yosef ben Shimons,
okay? And this was Charlie owes יוסף בן שמעון, Yosef ben Shimon,
right, a thousand dollars. Okay.
And now
here's the לווה. loveh. לווה, Loveh, here's Charlie. And he found
a receipt. And he didn't find a receipt. He's got a receipt.
Okay, and the receipt says, you know, יוסף בן שמעון's Yosef ben
Shimon שטר shtar is paid up. Okay. And this יוסף בן שמעון
Yosef ben Shimon has a שטר shtar that says Charlie... I borrowed
from both יוסף בן שמעון. Yosef ben Shimons. Charlie used, Charlie, sorry,
יוסף בן שמעון, Yosef ben Shimon, right, ten thousand dollars, okay? I
borrowed from both of these guys. All right, you got it? Now,
wait a minute, it
says נמצא ללווה, nimtza leloveh, doesn't mean he found it?
No, it means he produced it. It was in his possession. Okay.
So, so this is the flip case, it's not, right? This is
the case of that the creditors have the same name. But it's
more complicated, because it's not just I'm believed and I don't have
to be concerned that it came from whatever. Both creditors lent with
the same name, lent to the same guy, okay? So each one
of us, without this receipt I'll go collect my thousand, we assume
that the שטר shtar I'm holding is mine.
He'll collect his thousand, we assume the שטר shtar he's holding is
his.
But he has got a receipt that says יוסף בן שמעון's Yosef
ben Shimon שטר shtar is paid up. So now neither of us
can collect. That receipt neutralizes both שטרות. shtarot. Okay? And is the
sign of- is the receipt signed by- well, we have witnesses, yeah.
No, because I'm thinking- check this- No, it's not necessarily signed by
the creditor. It's witnessed. Okay, so it's the flip. It's not you're
trying to get the money from יוסף בן שמעון, Yosef ben Shimon,
יוסף בן שמעון Yosef ben Shimon is trying to get the money
from you. Both יוסף בן שמעוןs Yosef ben Shimon have שטרות shtarot
against you. If your thing just says יוסף בן שמעון's Yosef ben
Shimon שטר shtar is paid up, it's a get out of jail
free card. But the רשב"ם Rashbam now says, what the רשב"ם Rashbam
says, the two of us can go ahead and write a power
of attorney. So I can go ahead and-
now, I can't collect the ten thousand
because he can always
claim it's the ten thousand.
But this one can go ahead and write a power of attorney
to this guy, and this guy will come and say, "You owe
me at least a thousand dollars. Either you owe me a thousand
dollars because of my debt, or you owe me even more than
a thousand dollars because of this other יוסף בן שמעון's Yosef ben
Shimon debt. That thing would only have eliminated one of the two
claims, but regardless, you owe me at least a thousand dollars." So
if we're able to essentially come as one court case and not
two, he'll have to pay up the lower amount. But if we
come individually, each one, he just claims, "I don't owe you anything."
Yeah, Joe. In one, did it say שוברי shovari in that case,
or משולש? meshulash? That would have solved... Obviously, yeah. What's the phrase
that the רשב"ם Rashbam uses for power of attorney? הרשאה. harsha'a. Ah,
it's right, שטר הרשאה. shtar harsha'a. Yeah, yeah, yeah. Can the witnesses
be used to identify which of the two... Yeah, if the witnesses
come and remember and testify, then definitely. Okay. All right. So that's
what it says. So let's just read that again. אמר אביי הכי
קאמר, amar Abaye hachi kama, this is what it's saying.
נמצא ללווה בין שטרותיו, nimtza leloveh bein shtarotav, שטר שיוסף בן שמעון
עלי, shtar sheYosef ben Shimon alay, the שטר shtar that יוסף בן
שמעון Yosef ben Shimon has against me, יוסף בן שמעון Yosef ben
Shimon is the creditor. פרוע, parua, שטר שניהם פרועים. shtar sheneihem paruim.
Both of the שטרות shtarot of the two יוסף בן שמעוןs
Yosef ben Shimon are effectively paid up. כיצד יעשו?
keitzad ya'asu? ישלשו. yashalshu.
How do you deal with this? If it's the same names, you
write
three generations.
תניא אם היו שניהם כהנים, tanya im hayu sheneihem Kohanim, and if
they're both כהנים Kohanim or both ישראלים, Yisraelim, because that was the
final resort of the משנה. Mishnah. יכתבו דורות, yichtevu dorot, then do
four generations, five generations, okay? Again, as I pointed out, it's not
even in the גמרא's Gemara radar to maybe use the names of
mothers or grandmothers. Yes. There's one question I had from yesterday about
a partial payment. Do you have to accept... I do not want
to go there now. Next משנה. Mishnah. האומר לבנו, ha'omer livno, שטר
בין שטרותי פרוע ואיני יודע איזהו. shtar bein shtarotai parua ve'eini yodeia
eizehu. So here again is an interesting case of like an honest
person. He's on his deathbed, he wants to make sure that he
has a clean slate. And he says, "You know what? I remember
with all- I have a thousand שטרות, shtarot, I have- and- but
one of them is paid up. And I don't remember which one
paid up." Okay.
שטרות כולם פרועים. shtarot kulam paruim. You have to treat them all
as paid up and you can't collect any.
Now the interesting question I have here is, you know, is this
just because of like מצוה לקיים דברי המת? mitzvah lekayem divrei hameis?
It sounds like legally that prevents the son from doing it. So
what principle is that based on? Is it based on the principle
of like- of like הודאת בעל דין כמאה עדים דמי? hoda'at ba'al
din kemei'a eidim dami? He's the one who's owed money, he's admitting
while he's still alive that he doesn't know. So we take his
own admission- that one guy paid up, we take his own admission,
right? And then, you know, but it's pretty funny that there's such
an idea of הודאת בעל דין hoda'at ba'al din by a ספק,
safek, right? One of these things is paid up and I don't
know which one. And that's then sort of like, you know, prevents-
is that really an admission? You know, apparently it is. It's enough
of an admission to say that it neutralizes the use of any
שטר. shtar. What? It had to do with a שטר, shtar, right?
He could have said this in anything. Yeah, yeah, but that would
be a scenario. Okay, then why is the son the one now
coming to court? Because he's dead already. Okay. נמצא לאחד שם שנים
הגדול פרוע והקטן אינו פרוע. nimtza le'echad sham shenayim hagadol parua vehakatan
eino parua. Now let's say that I said one of the שטרות
shtarot is paid up. Okay, the guy's- one of the שטרות shtarot
is paid up. But a certain person, Charlie, has the- you know,
he has two שטרות shtarot
against Charlie, a ten thousand dollar and a one thousand.
So he can at least collect the one thousand, right? Because worst
case scenario, he meant the ten thousand dollar of Charlie. So the
one thing you know is the one possibility is that anybody else
might not owe him anything. Their שטרות shtarot are paid up. But
Charlie, who that there's two שטרות shtarot against Charlie, certainly owes him
at least a thousand dollars. So that one you can collect. Okay.
So says the גמרא, Gemara, אמר רבא שטר לך בידי פרוע. amar
Rava shtar lecha beyadi parua. If I go and I say to
Michael, "Michael, that שטר shtar that I have against you, it's paid
up," I admit that. And I have two שטרות shtarot against you.
הגדול פרוע והקטן אינו פרוע, hagadol parua vehakatan eino parua, same idea.
I can't collect the larger amount, but if I have two שטרות
shtarot against you, I can collect the lesser amount. Because either way,
you owe me at least the lesser amount. Either the larger one
is paid up or the smaller one. paid up, but minimally you
owe me the lesser amount. Now if I say חוב שלך בידי
פרוע, hov shelecha beyadi paruah, the debt you owe me is paid
up, not the שטר shtar is paid up, שטרות כולן פרועין, shtarot
kulan paruin, then even if I have two שטרות shtarot against you,
I can't collect either because the debt means the entire debt. אמר
ליה רבינא לרבא, Amar lei Ravina le-Rava, so Ravina said to Rava,
אלא מעתה, ela me'ata, so that's true if we interpret things to
be you know so much to the favor of things being abstract,
all debts you owe me so to speak. Yeah, the debt could
be the total amount you owe me. אלא מעתה, ela me'ata, if
we interpret those indeterminate phrases to the benefit of the other party,
if I say שדי מכור לך, sadi machur lach, if Michael has
a שטר shtar from me that says I sold you my field
and I have a lot of fields, should we say it
means שדה גדולה מכורה לו, sada gedola mechura lo, he should assume
the bigger one?
Because here too if I say it's paid up we assume the
bigger one is paid up. So if I say the field, doesn't
it mean the bigger field? Or moving along, שדה שיש לי מכור
לך, sade sheyesh li machur lach, and if I say the field
that I have is sold to you, should I say כל שדותיו
מכורים, kol sadotav mechurim, means all of them? Do we interpret them,
would you say a parallel thing by a sale, a bill of
sale? So no, he says no, התם יד בעל השטר
על התחתונה.
Hatam yad ba'al
hashtar al hatachtona.
The burden of proof is
on the person with the שטר, shtar, meaning in both cases it's
not that we know what those words mean, it's a case of
a ספק. safek. So if I basically say to Michael one of
your שטרות shtarot is paid up, okay, then I have to prove,
the burden of proof is on me, so I have to take
the lesser, I have to assume that the bigger one was paid
up and not the smaller one. But if Michael has a שטר
shtar that says I, Dov, sold Michael my field, then he's trying
to take my field away from me, so he has to prove
that it's the bigger one and not, if he can't prove it
we'll assume it's the smaller one. So the point is the word
itself doesn't mean the bigger debt or the bigger field, the point
is that it's indeterminate and it's essentially המוציא מחברו עליו הראיה. hamotzi
mechavero alav hara'aya. Isn't this, why not make us say like הפה
שאסר הוא הפה שהתיר? hapeh she-asar hu hapeh she-hitir? If you say,
we don't know, the only way we know one of these חובות
chovot are פרוע parua is because you're claiming it. There's no receipt,
there's no nothing, right? Correct. So why can't you say oh yeah,
one of your חוב chov is paid up but it's really the
thousand dollars?
If you said that you'd be believed, but you didn't. You don't
know. You don't know. Right, right, he means שטר, shtar, but either
way you don't know, that's the point. Okay, המלווה את חבירו, Hamalveh
et chavero, now we are switching gears from this case about two
Reuven ben Shimons and
ספק safek and so on to talk about an actual, a new
principle, the principle of a co-signer. כל ישראל ערבים זה בזה, kol
Yisrael arevim ze bazeh, okay, or it should be ערבים זה לזה
arevim ze lazah because ערב arev doesn't mean like intertwined, it means
an ערב arev as a guarantor, okay? So when you're a guarantor
for somebody, if I'm a guarantor for Michael's loan, a co-signer for
his loan, it means that if he defaults the creditor can come
to me. So if I'm an ערב arev for him in the
world of מצוות, mitzvot, it means that if Michael isn't doing his
obligations God can come and ask me why he's defaulted on his
loans and he's going to take that from me. Okay, so that's
the principle of ערב arev here, it's a legal principle of a
debt but it gets abstracted to this sense of responsible for one
another in a religious sense. So now we're going to look at
this. המלווה את חבירו על ידי ערב, Hamalveh et chavero al yedei
arev, I lend money through a guarantor, all right? לא יפרע מן
הערב תחילה. lo yifra min ha-arev techila. So okay, basically, so I
go ahead and I lend Michael money but I know that he
sometimes has defaulted on his loans and I'm very hesitant to lend
him money, so David steps up to the plate and David says
I'll co-sign, I'll be a guarantor, okay? So now when I come
to בית דין, Beit Din, I can't go straight to David.
I have to first
go to Michael and it's only if Michael defaults that I can
then go to the guarantor. ואם אמר לו על מנת שאפרע ממי
שארצה, ve-im amar lo al menat she-efra mimi she-ertzeh, but if I
say, but if Michael says, excuse me, if I say Michael, I'm
lending you this money with David here as the guarantor, but I'm
reserving for myself the right to go to whoever I want, to
collect it from whoever I want, to go straight to David, so
יפרע מן הערב, yifra min ha-arev, I can go straight to David.
David has to be there and agree to this. Yeah, yeah, of
course. That has to be in writing? Yeah, what, it has to
be in the loan, I hear David has to sign, I hereby
agree to this? No, you need witnesses or whatever, not necessarily sign,
but obviously it all has to be shown that David agreed to
it.
רבן שמעון בן גמליאל אומר אם יש
נכסים ללווה בין כך ובין כך לא יפרע מן
הערב.
Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel omer im yesh nechasim laloveh bein kach uvein
kach lo
yifra min ha-arev.
No, no, no.
Even if I said I get to choose who I go to
first, as long as Michael still has some available assets I don't
have a right to go to David. Okay, so, what point is
he saying, I mean you know, I'll discuss that. Okay, the point
could be like how obvious is it that you have assets, right?
There's like going to be a middle case, I'll mention it
now, but we'll be more specific about
it in a minute, but the middle case is where you don't
have any obvious assets, you don't have any land, you don't have
any, it's not like we know you've got a big bank account,
can I just go straight to David or do I have to
take you to court and we have to do a the search
for your assets or what discovery and whatever, and only when it's
clear you've defaulted am I entitled to go to David. So there
are like two degrees of אין לו נכסים, ein lo nechasim, okay?
So Rashbag and I presumably Rashbag means if it's obvious that the
לווה loveh has נכסים, nechasim, then even if I've made this claim,
I can't go straight to David. But anyway, we'll see more about
this in the גמרא. Gemara. Okay, וכן היה רבן שמעון בן גמליאל
אומר, Ve-chen hayah Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel omer, Rabban Shimon used to
say הערב לאשה בכתובתה, ha-arev le-ishah be-khutuvatah, והיה בעלה מגרשה, ve-hayah ba'alah
megashah, this really is not related... I mean it's about a guarantor
but it's not... it's not the same point as before. Okay, so
David here was a co-signer for my כתובה ketubah for my wife.
Okay, so basically I signed this כתובה ketubah for my wife which
said, you know, that if I divorce you I'm going to give
you ten thousand dollars, and my wife said, uh-uh, I know you're
not so sure you're going to have that money to pay me
up if we ever I ever get divorced. I'm not marrying you
unless you get somebody to co-sign the כתובה. ketubah. Okay, this just
reminds us that the כתובה ketubah was a real legal document. So
David, my pal here, steps up and says, no, okay, I'll co-sign...
not you know I'll be a guarantor to the כתובה. ketubah. If
Dov doesn't have the money to pay and he divorces you, I'll
pay for him. So David is the ערב arev for my כתובה,
ketubah, okay? And I look... and I was in the process of
divorcing my wife. Okay, so we've got a problem. You know what
problem we've got is? I might have a little scheme going on
with my wife. You know what the scheme is? I'm going to
divorce you, I right now have no money, you will then collect
your כתובה ketubah from David, get your ten thousand dollars from David,
and then we'll get remarried. Okay, perfect. Okay, so what do we
do to prevent that? ידירנה הנאה. yadirenah hana'ah. When I'm divorcing her
I have to say I cannot get any הנאה hana'ah from you
ever again, okay, which means that I won't be able to remarry
her. Okay, and I also won't be able to get any money
that she has. Okay, שמא יעשו קנוניא, she-ma ya'asu knunya, because we're
afraid that the husband and wife are doing a little like of
a scheme על נכסים של זה, al nechasim shel zeh, to take
the property from the guarantor, ויחזיר אשתו, ve-yahazir ishto, and he'll remarry
his wife. Okay, so that's a different issue from the question of
who do you get to go to first.
Let's take a look at the גמרא. Gemara. You never really have
an ערב arev if you
you'd ever plan to get remarried...
it might work for a כהן Kohen or something like that because
he can't marry her...
No, you can have an ערב arev if you do it through
this ידירנה הנאה. yadirenah hana'ah. No, I know, but if you ever
want to remarry her, you don't want to do that. Right. Couldn't
you have the נדר neder of... so the Rashbam says you do
it with a נדר על דעת רבים neder al da'at rabbim in
a way that's impossible to revoke and so on. Right. We'll see
that in the גמרא. Gemara. מאי טעמא? Mai ta'ama? Now what is
the reason that you can't go straight to the ערב? arev? You
could have asked what's the reason that we have a principle of
ערב, arev, how do we know there is such a logic as
a guarantor? Like David here never borrowed money from me, just because
he says that he's going to be... you know he'll protect you
know if Michael defaults he'll take the responsibility, what makes him obligate?
Okay, so we'll get to that, but now we're actually focusing on
why how do we know assuming there is this institution of ערב
arev how do we know I can't go to David first once
he's accepting responsibility? So רבא ורב יוסף דאמרי תרווייהו, Rava ve-Rav Yosef
d-amri tarvaihu, Rava and Rav Yosef both say גברא אשלמית לי גברא
אשלמי לך. gavra ashlimit li gavra ashlimi lach. So they understand that
really what David's role is, I think the best way of sort
of of thinking about this is like a bail bondsman, okay, that
David's job is really not to pay. David's job is to make
sure that Michael doesn't run away. All right? So that and the
only time David would pay would be if Michael has completely skipped
town and there's nowhere to find him and then David is going
to pay for Michael. But his basic principle is to make sure
that Michael makes it to court. And then even if Michael has
no money I can't collect from David. David's only responsibility is to
produce Michael. If he doesn't produce Michael then he'll have to pay.
Okay, so that's what David says. David says I have גברא, gavra,
let's see that again, אשלמית לי, ashlimit li, you have basically entrusted
to me a person, I've taken responsibility over the debtor, גברא אשלמי
לך, gavra ashlimi lach, I'm giving you back the debtor and then
he's free. Okay, now that very much narrows the responsibility of the
ערב arev only to when the debtor is no longer around. So
מתקיף לה רב נחמן, maskif lah Rav Nachman, so Rav Nachman asked
this, האי דינא דפרסאי? hai dina de-Parsaye? That's the way Persians deal
with the idea of an ערב. arev. That's not our way of
dealing with an ערב, arev, okay? So now the גמרא Gemara says
no, that's actually not the way. אדרבה, Adaraba, בתר ערבא אזלי, batar
areva azli, the Persians actually their law is actually to let you
go straight to the ערב. arev. So what do you mean this
is a Persian ruling? So the גמרא Gemara says אלא, ela, no,
בדינא דפרסאי, be-dina de-Parsaye, you're acting like a Persian court when you
say such a thing, דלא יהיב טעמא למלתייהו, de-lo yahiv ta'ama le-miltayhu,
in Persian courts they just you know they issue their rulings ex
cathedra, they don't give any reasons for it. So what you're saying
is like a crazy idea, you know? You're saying that all David
has to do is produce is to produce Michael. That's... what's the
logic of that?
The idea of a guarantor means that he's accepting part of the
responsibility of the loan. Why should I interpret it to mean what
he's basically doing is just ensuring
that he'll produce the debtor? The debtor. Point of a cosigner, a
guarantor whatever is is if I don't pay. Not that you go,
that's what he's signing up for. That's like, isn't that my question
that, why don't you go to the guarantor to... No no, the
question that... All right, fine, we'll get back to that. But right
now we're working with this claim, okay? This claim tried to extremely
limit the idea of a guarantor that even if Michael doesn't have
money, once Michael's in court, I can't go to the guarantor. And
the גמרא Gemara says that's crazy. As Michael just said, the purpose
of a guarantor is to protect the loan, not just to produce
the debtor. So why should I, why should I read it in
that narrow way? So אלא מרב נחמן, Ella mi-Rav Nachman, okay, they're
right. The guarantor is liable for the loan, not just for producing
the debtor. But why can't I go to the guarantor first? מאי
לא יפרע מן הערב? Mai lo yifra min ha-areiv? No, because part
of the problem is what words did we have in our משנה?
Mishnah? Our משנה Mishnah says, what does our משנה Mishnah say? לא
יפרע מן הערב. Lo yifra min ha-areiv. It sounds like I was
adding in the word because I was already, you know, anticipating the
גמרא, Gemara, תחילה. techila. Don't go to the ערב areiv first. But
the simple interpretation of the words of the משנה Mishnah is David
is the guarantor and David never has to pay. Okay? לא יפרע
מן הערב, Lo yifra min ha-areiv, I can never collect from David.
So the גמרא Gemara is saying that doesn't make any sense. So
now we're going to say, no no, let me clarify. It doesn't
mean you can't collect from him. It means you can't go to
him first. Okay? מאי לא יפרע מן הערב, Mai lo yifra min
ha-areiv, it doesn't mean all David has to do is produce Michael.
But no, it means לא יתבע ערב תחילה. Lo yitba areiv techila.
Obviously the idea of guarantor is assuming some of the responsibility of
the loan, but he's the second level of defense, meaning he is
the backup. I can't go to him first. All right. תניא נמי
הכי Tanya nami hachi we taught similarly,
המלווה את חברו
על ידי ערב,
Ha-malveh et
chaveiro
al yedai areiv, לא יתבע ערב תחילה. lo yitba areiv techila. So
the key is the word תחילה. techila. It's not that he's not
liable, but he cannot be the first person I go to. ואם
אמר על מנת שאפרע ממי שארצה, Ve-im amar al menat she-eifra mi-mi
she-ertzeh, יתבע ערב תחילה. yitba areiv techila. But if I stipulate and
say I can go to whoever I want, then I can go
straight to him. Typically we would disagree and we're going to modify
that in a minute anyway. אמר רב הונא מנין לערב דמשתעבד. Amar
Rav Huna minayin le-areiv de-mishta'abed. Now we get to the question of,
fine, we've clarified that the ערב areiv is liable just at a
second level, okay? But now where do we get this idea that
you have a whole institution of ערב? areiv? And משתעבד mishta'abed means
like, you know, like משתעבד mishta'abed and the key here is going
to be or one of the ways is that the question, you
could just say conceptually where is this idea from at all together?
But it's also a question about how do you know that just
verbally, David says I will agree... Now where I've been saying, you
know, interchangeable word guarantor and cosigner because that's
what we do,
it's we get somebody to cosign. But according to the הלכה, Halacha,
all David has to do is when I'm lending money to Michael
and there are witnesses, David says don't worry I'll be a guarantor.
I'm saying I'm not sure I want to lend money to Michael,
David says don't worry I'll be a guarantor. And witnesses hear him
say it and I lend money to Michael and he's liable. So
that's a pretty big חידוש, chiddush, that just by saying those words
he becomes obligated. Okay. Why is that? What it is? That's what
it is? No, a normal way is if I wanted to obligate
myself to you in a vacuum, I would have to do at
least a קניין, kinyan, a קניין סודר. kinyan sudar.
I could take a סודר, sudar, you know, or my whatever and
say like, you know, if XYZ happens I'll owe Michael a thousand
dollars. So if David took a סודר sudar and says if
Michael doesn't pay I'll owe
Dov a thousand dollars, that's a normal התחייבות, hitchayvut, obligating yourself through
a מעשה קניין, ma'aseh kinyan, through taking a סודר. sudar. Okay, but
that's not what he does.
And so if you had that mechanism it would make sense. But
all he did was he verbally said I'll be a guarantor. Okay?
And how do we know that verbal thing creates this status of
a guarantor? So I wasn't appreciating the question. So in other words
the question is how could he be, how could he emerge legally
obligated without a mechanism that we would normally look for? Right. It's
like a, but you know it's just like sort of a גלגול
קניין. gilgul kinyan. Like a, like... Well okay, that might be, but
let's see how the גמרא Gemara explains it, okay? But it's could
be like a double level of question. Where do we know this
institution exists all together and how do you create it just through
words? Okay? דכתיב, De-chtiv, because it says, אנכי אערבנו מידי תבקשנו. Anochi
e'erevenu mi-yadi tevakshenu. I will be a guarantor, you can ask him
for me by בנימין Binyamin if I do not produce him. I
will be liable.
Now of course the funny thing is is that who is the
borrower in that case? So it sounds like
יוסף Yosef is the borrower, you know. Give it, give him to
be brought over to מצרים, Mitzrayim, like I'm not taking בנימין Binyamin
for myself, I'm not taking him home making him my slave, you
know. We're sort of delivering him as it were to יוסף Yosef
in מצרים. Mitzrayim. יוסף Yosef is the borrower and if יוסף Yosef
the borrower doesn't give him back then you can come to me.
Okay. Which he does. Which is what actually, you know, יהודה Yehuda
does because he says, he says give it to his father, he
offers himself to יוסף Yosef so that יוסף Yosef can go back.
Exactly. Okay, yeah. Right, exactly. Thank you, yeah. So that shows that.
So מתקיף לה רב חסדא, Matkif lah Rav Chisda, Rav Chisda asked
this, הא קבלנות היא. ha kablanut hi. דכתיב, De-chtiv, תנה... Tneh... Give
him to me and I will return him. That's not ערבות, areivus,
that's קבלנות. kablanus. Now what's the difference between קבלנות kablanus and ערבות?
areivus? So קבלנות kablanus means when I directly say, I say here,
you know, David, you say, I'm considering whether to lend money to
Michael, and you say to me, you say to me, Dov, give,
lend the money
to Michael and I will pay it up.
Okay, so that is more than saying I'm a guarantor. Okay, you
are telling me, effectively this is sort of like what Dov was
saying about this idea of like piggyback, you are effectively saying by
you lending money to Michael, it's like you've lent the money to
me and I'll be the one liable. So you don't have to
go to me at all? What? That means you don't have to
go to me at all. Right, well, it could be that
קבלנות kablanus allows me
to go straight
to David and we'll discuss that.
Okay, but it's a subtle difference, but is David saying I'll be
a guarantor and then I'm sort of lending money to Michael and
he's putting himself somewhere in the background there as a guarantor? Or
is he getting directly involved in the actual process and says, Dov,
you lend him the money and it'll be my responsibility. What is
that called in English? I have no idea what it's called. Such
a concept. It's ערב קבלן. arev kablan. Right, it's ערב קבלן, arev
kablan, yeah. So I have no idea what whether that's a difference
in English law
about secular law about that.
But that's the גמרא's Gemara point, it says תנהו על ידי ואני
אשיבנו אליך. tenahu oso al yadi vaani ashivenu alecha. Give him and
it'll be my responsibility. So you're not just saying I will be
a guarantor, okay, you're saying, you know, you know, you're directly involving
yourself, you're talking about the act of lending the money, if you
lend it, that'll be my responsibility. So it's sort of like you're
putting yourself in as the direct party. It's almost transferring the debt.
Exactly. Okay, so that's not a proof for the general idea of
ערבות areivus when you're more in the background. אלא אמר רב יצחק
מהכא, Ela amar Rav Yitzchak me-hacha, from here. לקח בגדו כי ערב
זר, Lakach bigdo ki areiv zar, he took his garment because he
became, you know, because you were, you made yourself a guarantor to
a stranger. Like this is sort of like, you know, in משלי,
Mishlei, like, you know, don't get, you know, don't be stupid. So
if you're making yourself like Shakespeare, neither a borrower nor lender be.
You go ahead and you make yourself a guarantor to a stranger,
you should expect that your garment has been taken from you. You
know, he's going to default on the loan and you're going to
have your garment taken from you. ובעד נכריה חבלהו Uve-ad nachriachavlohu and
from a because of a foreign person it was taken as collateral.
So anyway, it reflects the idea that there's this idea of guarantor
and as a result of being a guarantor, your property could be
seized from you. ואומר, Ve-omer, and the verse says, בני, beni, my
son, אם ערבת לרעך, im aravta lere'echa, if you became a guarantor
for your friend, תקעת לזר כפיך, takata lezar kapecha, you shook your
hand with the, you know, you made a deal with a stranger.
נוקשת, Nokashta, maybe the stranger there is the I don't know the
lender. נוקשת באמרי פיך Nokashta be-imre picha or if you have stumbled
on the words of your lips, נלכדת באמרי פיך, nilkadta be-imre picha,
it's double, everything is sort of being doubled here. עשה זאת אפוא
בני והנצל, asei zos eifo beni vehinatzel, do this and be saved,
כי באת בכף רעך, ki vasa be-kaf re'echa, if you came into
the hand of your friend, meaning this is presumably the case of
the shaking of the hand, the being the guarantor, לך התרפס ורהב
רעך, lech hitrapas u-rehav re'echa, go and, you know, I don't know
how they translate that, but go here it's being understood as, you
know, go and supplicate your friend or go, but here it means
go and pay up the debt because you made this deal. אם
ממון יש לו בידך, Im mammon yesh lo be-yadecha, so now here's
the גמרא Gemara going to interpret, if now as a result you
owe money because you became a guarantor, התר פיסת יד, hater pisat
yad, so התרפס, hitrapas, התר פיסת יד, hater pisat yad, open up
your hand and now pay because you became a guarantor. ואם לאו,
Ve-im lav, now ורהב רעך u-rehav re'echa means is a word of
הרבה רעים. harbeh re'im. That's the way it's being read. הרבה לו
רעים, harbeh lo re'im, have a lot of friends come in to
try to ameliorate the person and so on. So anyway, the point
though being is it uses the word ערב areiv and it's clearly
indicating that a guarantor becomes liable for the loan. Okay, so now
let's, I just want to read to the two dots, give me
one more minute because now we're going to get directly to the
case of, fine, you showed it in the פסוקים, pesukim, but what
exactly is the mechanism? So the גמרא Gemara says, אמר מר, amar
mar, ערב משתעבד, areiv mishtabeid, מחלוקת machlokes רבי יהודה ורבי יוסי. Rabbi
Yehuda ve-Rabbi Yose. This issue whether an ערב areiv can really become
liable just by agreeing to be an ערב, areiv, it's very nice
you showed it in the פסוקים pesukim or whatever, but whether it
legally works is a debate of רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda and רבי
יוסי. Rabbi Yose. לרבי יוסי דאמר, Le-Rabbi Yose de-amar, אסמכתא קניא, asmachta
kanya, ערב משתעבד. areiv mishtabeid. If you say, so besides the question
of words versus קנין, kinyan, there's one question of the mechanism, right,
is it just verbally agreeing or did you do a קנין kinyan
which normally you need as the mechanism to create a debt? But
it's also an obligation that you're expecting never to have to pay.
I'm saying that I'll be a guarantor in order to get the
lender to lend money to my friend, but I'm never, I'm hoping
and certainly I never really want to pay that debt. I really
just want him to lend money to my friend. So that's an
אסמכתא. asmachta. You're promising something that you hope you'll never have to
do. So besides the mechanism issue, there's the אסמכתא asmachta issue. Okay,
רבי יוסי Rabbi Yosei דאמר d'amar אסמכתא קניא, asmachta kanya, ערב משתעבד,
arev mishtabed, and ערב arev does become indebted. רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda
דאמר d'amar אסמכתא לא קניא, asmachta lo kanya, ערב לא משתעבד. arev
lo mishtabed. He doesn't become indebted, okay, even though—so besides the mechanism,
there's the question of: Are you really committing to pay? So now
the גמרא Gemara says, "But one minute, we've got a problem." אמרי
ליה רב אשי לאמימר, Amrei leh Rav Ashi l'Amemar, so רב אשי
Rav Ashi said to אמימר, Amemar, המעשים בכל יום hama'asim b'chol yom
דאסמכתא לא קניא. d'asmachta lo kanya. First of all, when cases of
אסמכתא asmachta come to court, we throw them out. Okay, we say
אסמכתא לא קניא, asmachta lo kanya, that's not a binding obligation, cases
of אסמכתא. asmachta. And number two, וערב משתעבד. va'arev mishtabed. When cases
of guarantors come to court, we rule on them. So we have
the institution of guarantors even though we say אסמכתא לא קניא. asmachta
lo kanya. So what's the answer, right? How do you do this?
Right? Why isn't that just an אסמכתא? asmachta? Says the גמרא, Gemara,
אלא אמר רב אשי בהאי הנאה דקמהימין ליה גמר ומשתעבד נפשיה. Ela
amar Rav Ashi be-hai hana'ah de-kamheimin leh gemar mishtabed nafsheh. Since I
know that by agreeing to be a ערב, arev, you are relying
on me, right? So it's basically, it's like, it's not just like,
"Oh, I get some הנאה, hana'ah, everybody looks, oh, Dov is such
a great guy, he cosigned loans, etc." No, I think it's deeper
than that. What it's saying is is that I know you're only
lending the money because you're trusting me to pay up if I
have to pay up. So since I know that that's why you're
lending the money, I really am planning on paying up. Like that's
essentially like, you know, I lent money because of your promise, because
you made a commitment. So, you know, if you're any person with
integrity, you really have to be prepared to pay up because you
know this person is relying on you. All right, so since you
know that this person is lending the money because they are depending
on the veracity and on the commitment behind your word, even though
it's only—you don't really want to have to do it, you really
are committing to do it if it's necessary. Like the ערב arev
is getting the הנאה hana'ah that the מלוה malveh believes in his
integrity. Right, right. That's amazing. Yeah, but I would reframe it a
little bit like הנאה, hana'ah, like "Oh, isn't that so nice people
trust me." I would reframe it as like because you understand that
he's lending money only because of your commitment, you know, and he
is relying on you. That's הנאה. hana'ah. Yeah, but it's right, right,
but I don't think you have to use the word הנאה. hana'ah.
I think you could use more words like integrity, right, you know,
you understand that then you really are committing, you really are committing
to pay up. Okay, so on the one hand we have the
idea that ערב arev doesn't need a קנין, kinyan, it's just the
words, it's a commitment to be the ערב, arev, and even though
it's a type of an אסמכתא, asmachta, he hopes to never have
to pay, because it's on this basis that the money was lent,
he really is committing to pay and even though אסמכתא לא קניא,
asmachta lo kanya, right, ערב arev is a binding obligation. Okay, so
we will deal with tomorrow—turn to this question of the order
of
who
pays up
first.